

## **Hunter Ratliff**

Nuclear Engineer, Researcher, and Code Developer

- 23 June 1993
- Skytterveien 31, 5038 Bergen, Norway
- **)** (+47) 46 26 55 39
- hratliff.com
- @ hunter@hratliff.com
- in linkedin.com/in/hunter-ratliff United States citizenship
- Norwegian residence

## Skills -

#### Languages

- English Norwegian
- Programming
- Python, Jupyter Fortran (IV/77/90/08)

C++

- **MATLAB** 
  - CMD/Bash scripting
- Git, GitHub Nuclear / Scientific
- - DCHAIN (activation)

PHITS, MCNP6/X/5

- SCALE/ORIGEN
- **ROOT**
- Other
- LaTeX, TikZ, MetaPost ●
  - HPC (MPI/OpenMP, Slurm) ● ●
    - HTML, CSS, Markdown • • •

Microsoft Office Suite • •

DOS/Unix CLI, SSH

- **Hunter Ratliff** Nuclear Engineer, Researcher,

and Code Developer

Programming and scripting

Specialties -

- Monte Carlo methods/simulation
- Data analysis and visualization
- Nuclear data processing/formatting

Documentation and presentation

Web design/online tool development

# Professional Bio —

Hunter studied for a BS in nuclear engineering at the University of Tennessee from 2011 to 2015 and, when presented with interesting space radiation research opportunities, continued with his graduate studies at UTK, earning a PhD in late 2018. Afterward, he moved to Japan in early 2019 to join the PHITS code development team at the Japan Atomic Energy Agency. In 2021 he then moved to Norway to research neutron/ $\gamma$ -ray imaging for proton radiotherapy at The Western Norway University of Applied Sciences.

# Personal Bio -

After living his entire life in the US state of Tennessee, Hunter made his first trip abroad: moving to Japan. Since, he has wholly enjoyed exploring the scenery, cultures, and languages everywhere he has lived. New experiences in travel, cuisine, and forces of nature have truly opened his eyes to the staggering variety of experiences the world has to offer on his now-international journey through life.

## Other -

- Norway category B driving license
- Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America
- Uni. pedagogy education HVL/ALU Degrees, certificates, and any other documents available upon request

### **Summary**

Hunter is a nuclear engineer with experience in radiation transport simulations using PHITS and MCNP, activation and decay calculations, scientific code development in Python and Fortran, neutron and gamma-ray detection and imaging, space radiation modeling, cosmic-ray-like ion accelerator experiments, and analysis and visualization of large experimental and modeled datasets. He also has interests in radiation protection and shielding, radiotherapy, and radioisotope production.

#### Experience

- Oct. 2024 -Researcher
- Western Norway University of Applied Sciences (HVL) present Modeling relevant to proton therapy and associated range verification and imaging detection systems for experiment design and AI training; software tool development; continuation of work outlined below. Western Norway University of Applied Sciences (HVL)

oper of the DCHAIN-PHITS activation, buildup, burnup, and decay code coupled to PHITS. Implemented modern decay and cross sec-

tion libraries, uncertainty propagation, reaction tracking, tetrahedral and 3-D grid mesh geometry support, performance improvements,

new input/output features, and more into DCHAIN. Authored the user

Conducted accelerator experiments emulating radiation conditions within spacecraft, characterized resulting neutron spectra, and mod-

eled the experiments in MCNP. Also modeled the Martian surface's radiation environment from galactic cosmic rays in MCNP and PHITS

and modernized the CLSQ Fortran IV decay analysis code in Python.

Lead laboratory experience portions of courses within the Nuclear

Engineering Department, further developing skills in troubleshooting radiation detectors and associated pulse chain equipment, teaching,

communication, and providing constructive guidance to students.

Organized, conducted, and analyzed data from 400 hours of beam

experiments at the NASA Space Radiation Laboratory in Brookhaven

National Laboratory, characterizing the neutron environment within

(emulated) spacecraft bombarded by cosmic rays using established time-of-flight and newly developed deconvolution techniques. This

required substantial scripting to filter and process the raw data into

spectra and to generate, run, and process MCNPX/6 models of the experiment. Further detailed dose analyses were explored to draw

conclusions on optimal spacecraft shielding materials, thicknesses,

Designed and conducted MCNP6 simulations of the galactic cosmic

ray-induced radiation environment on the Martian surface, modeling

the individual particle spectra and dosimetric data as seen by the Radiation Assessment Detector onboard the Mars Curiosity Rover.

Designed a plate-fuel research reactor relevant to nuclear propulsion

fuels testing and modeled its criticality and shielding in MCNP for a

The Backscatter Gating method for time, energy, and position res-

Development of scalable deconvolution methods for determining

secondary target neutron yields from dual-thick-target cosmic-ray

H.N.Ratliff, N.A. McGirl, M.R. Beach, L.A. Castellanos, M.S. Clowdsley,

A hybrid multi-particle approach to range assessment-based treat-

I. Meric, E. Alagoz, L.B. Hysing, T. Kögler, D. Lathouwers, W.R.B.

Modernization of the DCHAIN-PHITS activation code with new fea-

**detector using MCNP6** *H.N. Ratliff, M.B.R. Smith, and L.H. Heilbronn* 

D. Matthiä, D.M. Hassler, W. de Wet, B. Ehresmann, A. Firan, J. Flores-

McLaughlin, J. Guo, L.H. Heilbronn, K. Lee, H.N. Ratliff, R.R. Rios, T.

Slaba, M.B.R. Smith, L.W. Townsend, T. Berger, G. Reitz, R.F. Wimmer-

Schweingruber, and C. Zeitlin, Life Sci. Space Res., 14C, 18–28, Jun. 2017.

proposed critical experiment facility as a final design project.

guide/manual and assisted with user support for DCHAIN-PHITS.

Japan Atomic Energy Agency (JAEA)

The University of Tennessee, Knoxville

- Aug. 2021 -Aug. 2024
- **Postdoctoral Fellow** Development, Monte Carlo modeling, experimental deployment, and data analysis of a prototype detector that is sensitive to and can image neutrons and gamma rays characteristic of those produced in

**Graduate Research Assistant** 

**Graduate Teaching Assistant** 

- patients receiving proton radiotherapy (for beam range verification). **Postdoctoral Fellow** Member of the PHITS particle transport code team as the lead devel-
- Apr. 2019 -Aug. 2021
- May 2015 -Feb. 2019
- Aug. 2015 -Dec. 2016
- **Education** May 2015 -Ph.D. in Nuclear Engineering
- May 2015 -

Dec. 2016

Grade: A (4.0/4.0)

Dec. 2018

Grade: A (4.0/4.0)

Aug. 2011 -May 2015

- Grade: A (3.94/4.0)
  - Selected Publications (full list: hratliff.com/publications/)

and configurations to minimize risk to astronauts.

M.S. in Nuclear Engineering

**B.S.** in Nuclear Engineering

2024

- olution characterization of long form factor organic scintillators H.N.Ratliff, T. Kögler, G. Pausch, L.M. Setterdahl, K. Skjerdal, J. Turko, and I. Meric, J. Instrum., 19, P07002, Jul. 2024. Characterization of organic glass scintillator bars and their poten-

2024

- tial for a hybrid neutron/gamma ray imaging system for proton radiotherapy range verification J. Turko, R. Beyer, A.R. Junghans, I. Meric, S.E. Mueller, G. Pausch, H.N.Ratliff, K. Römer, S.M. Schellhammer, L.M. Setterdahl, S. Urlass, A. Wagner, and T. Kögler, J. Instrum., 19, P01008, Jan. 2024.
- 2024
- Recent improvements of the Particle and Heavy Ion Transport code System - PHITS version 3.33 T. Sato, Y. Iwamoto, S. Hashimoto, T. Ogawa, T. Furuta, S. Abe, T. Kai, Y. Matsuya, N. Matsuda, Y. Hirata, T. Sekikawa, L. Yao, P. Tsai, H.N. Ratliff, H. Iwase, Y. Sakaki, K. Sugihara, N. Shigyo, L. Sihver, and K. Niita, J. Nucl. Sci. Technol., 61:1, 127-135, Jan. 2024.

2023

L.H. Heilbronn, C. La Tessa, J.W. Norbury, A. Rusek, M. Sivertz, A.P. Srikrishna, H. Wang, and C. Zeitlin Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, 544, 165121, Nov. 2023. 2023 Double-differential primary target neutron yields from dual-thick-

ion accelerator experiments

ment verification in particle therapy

tures and updated data libraries

- target proton and heavy ion accelerator experiments H.N. Ratliff, N.A. McGirl, M.R. Beach, L.A. Castellanos, M.S. Clowdsley, L.H. Heilbronn, C. La Tessa, J.W. Norbury, A. Rusek, M. Sivertz, A.P. Srikrishna, H. Wang, and C. Zeitlin Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, 542, 87-94, Sep. 2023.
- 2023
  - Lionheart, J. Mattingly, J. Obhodas, G. Pausch, H.E.S. Pettersen, H.N. Ratliff, M. Rovituso, S.M. Schellhammer, L.M. Setterdah, K. Skjerdal, E. Sterpin, D. Sudac, J.A. Turko, and K.S. Ytre-Hauge Scientific Reports, 13, 6709, Apr. 2023.
- 2020
- H.N. Ratliff, N. Matsuda, S. Abe, T. Miura, T. Furuta, Y. Iwamoto, T. Sato Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, 484, 29-41, Dec. 2020. 2017 Simulation of the GCR spectrum in the Mars Curiosity Rover's RAD
- Life Sciences in Space Research, 14, Suppl. C, 43–50, Jun. 2017. 2017 The radiation environment on the surface of Mars - Summary of model calculations and comparison to RAD data

Ref. 2

Ref. 3

#### References

- **Ilker Meric** Ref. 1 Supervisor; NOVO project PI
  - Associate Professor at The Western Norway Univ. of Applied Sciences sato.tatsuhiko@jaea.go.jp
  - **Tatsuhiko Sato**

Lawrence Heilbronn

Supervisor; Leader of the PHITS development team Senior Principal Researcher at Japan Atomic Energy Agency

Ph.D. advisor / Major professor

+1 865 974 2525 Professor at The University of Tennessee, Knoxville

**Hunter Ratliff** 

ilker.meric@hvl.no

+47 55 58 76 83

+81 29 282 5803

lheilbro@utk.edu